<ong>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>The World/People</cat>
<title>Gazpacho and Champagne</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Last year, to celebrate my unemployment, Lauren and I had a New Year’s Day
afternoon social, and it was a lot of fun, so we did it again this year, and
I think we’ll go on doing it.  The refreshments are those listed above, plus
hot lentil soup and cheeses and dips, and we didn’t offer desserts but a few
of the guests turned up with ’em and they got snaffled, so I guess we should
in future.  As for champagne, we find that the
<a href="http://www.mumm.com/eng/champ/ch_chrouge.htm">Mumm Cordon Rouge</a>
hits a good price-performance point.
The gazpacho (improvised by Lauren) was just stupendous, got raves all around.
The kids get sent upstairs where there are lots of toys and intermittent
supervision. We had one injury—somehow they managed to pull down a curtain and
the rod hit little Joe on the
head, nothing serious but it was kind of scary when he came downstairs
with bright red blood running down the side of his neck.
Oh, and someone broke the antenna off the toy-racecar remote, and Phil
Mansfield disassembled it on the spot and jacked in a new antenna made out of
the wire off a champagne cork, it worked fine, is that stylish or what?
The crowd included VCs, geeks, businesspeople, neighbours, parents of the
kid’s playmates, and miscellaneous old friends.  The thirty or forty people who
dropped by included only one other blogger, as far as I know, and very few
people who read <span class='o'>ongoing</span>; an 
indication, were any needed, that this public-voice thing is in its early
days.
Plus, Adam dropped off a mix disk labeled “CTI/Kudu (&amp; Others)”
which was just ultrasuede, luscious Boogie Nights Seventies organ funk.
Same time next year.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>The World/People</cat>
<cat>Technology/XML</cat>
<title>Ms Maler</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Hey,
<a href="http://www.xmlgrrl.com/blog/">Eve’s here</a>!
I expect great things.  What she doesn’t highlight in her basic
bio is that she helped invent XML, and has great hair, and is funny.
Oh, and dig her URL.
Now she’s a WordPress geek too; seems to be a growing tribe.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/XML</cat>
<cat>Technology/Web/Services</cat>
<title>UBL by the Numbers</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Via Jon Bosak, a pointer to
<a href="http://www.xmlconference.org/xmlusa/2004/slides/brun&amp;nielsen/Handling%201200%20Goverment%20Forms%20in%20XML%20Schema.ppt">this
XML 2004 presentation</a> (PowerPoint, sigh), about the Danish Government’s
deployment of a bunch of XML technologies including UBL.  
Check out slides 4 &amp; 5: they estimate the annual savings achievable from
invoicing in UBL at somewhere between €100M and €160M.
I may be out of step with the crowd but it seems
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2004/05/14/UBL10">painfully obvious</a> to me that
UBL is going to be huge and I don’t understand why more technology vendors
(including my employer) aren’t refocusing their e-business strategy around
it.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Mac OS X</cat>
<title>Another Mac Hint</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Herewith another Macintosh usability hint, plus an amplification of some
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2003/10/01/HowToUseOSX">previous advice</a>.</p>
<img class="inline" src="NoMinimize.png" alt="Don’t use yellow button" />
<h2 id='p-1'>Hide, Don’t Minimize</h2>
<p>Back in 2003 I
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2003/10/01/HowToUseOSX">offered some advice</a> on how to make the Dock useful;
one of them was never to click on that yellow “minimize” button.
Since then, I’ve come to appreciate the virtues of the OS X’s “Hide” function
(CMD-H in every app but PhotoShop, where it’s Shift-CMD-H). 
While, as noted, OS X, unlike Windows, deals well with tons of windows all
over the place, there’s no point keeping a window around for an app that I
use for 10 minutes once every other day, or for iTunes when it’s in
background-music shuffle mode.</p>
<p>Since no other popular GUI has a “hide” function as far as I know, the
utility may not be obvious to people like me who didn’t grow up in Mac-land,
but it’s actually real handy.</p>
<h2 id='p-2'>Extra Screen Where?</h2>
<p>When you plug an extra screen into a Mac, you can use the “Arrangement”
tab of the Displays preference to say where you want it, logically, and which
screen you want the menu-bar on.
Being a typically neatness-conscious geek, I had had the screens neatly lined
up at the top; but now I realize that makes the menu a little harder to get
to.</p>
<img src="Arrangement.png" alt="How to arrange your outboard screen" />
<div class="caption"><p>The right way to do it.</p></div>
<p>This way, to get to the menu, you go to the main screen and throw the
mouse to the top left or right corner, and because the tops aren’t lined off,
it can’t slide off into the other screen.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Publishing</cat>
<cat>Technology/Audio</cat>
<cat>Technology/Mac OS X</cat>
<title>Podcasting</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>I may not entirely get it, but I can’t ignore it, so herewith some
thoughts and predictions on the subject, plus obviously, a teeny little
podcast.</p>
<p>Let’s start with
Adam Curry’s Jan. 3rd <a href="http://www.curry.com/2005/01/03">Daily Source
Code</a>, which I listened to last night.
Adam points out that podcast-listening is an activity best suited to when
you’re chilling out, kicking back, getting high, whatever.
I’d re-spin that slightly to say it works best when you’re awake but doing
something that’s occupying only part of your attention.
The canonical example would be commuting, I guess, something I’ve carefully
structured my life to avoid.
But last night I was
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2003/03/27/Scanner">slide-scanning</a>, which
qualifies: (here’s a bit of the harvest: two cemetery shots, sometime in the
Eighties, from
the islands of Hawai’i and Kauai).</p>
<img src="0756.jpg" alt="Keopu Cemetery, island of Hawai’i" />
<img src="0809.jpg" alt="A cemetery on Kauai" />
<h2 id='p-1'>Would I Listen?</h2>
<p>Probably not to Adam; maybe once he gets past talking about podcasting
all the time, he’s probably more interesting on music and pop-culture.
He’s got a radio voice all right.
Maybe I’m just too much of a curmudgeon to enjoy cheerful
chatter about using Abba-tested techniques to protect your hair from your
headphones.  And frankly, if what Adam was passing along was the best of the
best from the podcast world, we’ve got a long way to go.
I find Dave Winer more content-ful, and he turns out to have a real
interesting voice.</p>
<p>But at the end of the day, I still think
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2004/10/11/Podcasting">the killer app is
music</a>.</p>
<p>And I’m pretty sure that when the subject is technology, I’d rather
read about it than hear about it.
One reason is the interactivity.</p>
<h2 id='p-2'>’casting Isn’t Conversing</h2>
<p>Any activity with “casting” in the name suggests one-to-many, and indeed,
I think podcasting is way less interactive than conventional blogging.
The reason is that when I’m reading a blog, I’m 100% engaged and I’m sitting
at a keyboard. 
If something strikes a chord, it’s a matter of seconds to write in response;
either one-on-one to the author, or to the author and the world via <span
class='o'>ongoing</span>.</p>
<p>Now, for listening to music, the interactivity deficit isn’t a problem.
But blogging is better than conventional publishing precisely because, at an
essential level, it’s two-way.</p>
<p>So I’m still waiting for musicians to start podcasting to route around
the wasteland of commercial music radio.</p>
<h2 id='p-3'>It’ll Catch On</h2>
<p>Whatever the right niche is, I’m betting that podcasting is going to catch
on fast and big, for one reason: it’s so incredibly easy.
To prove it, 
<enclosure href="20050104-1344.mp3">here</enclosure> is a little chunk of
audio, which has been duly flagged in my RSS feed as an
<code>&lt;enclosure></code>.</p>
<p>I got the idea this morning, and in between the usual email and phone
calls and other work, I figured out how to get
<a href="http://www.apple.com/quicktime/products/broadcaster/">QuickTime
Broadcaster</a> to record off the
<a href="http://www.apple.com/isight/">iSight’s</a> (fairly decent)
microphone, and then used Rogue Amoeba’s
<a href="http://www.rogueamoeba.com/audiohijackpro/">Audio Hijack Pro</a> to
turn that into an MP3, and then did a half-hour’s tinkering with the 
<span class='o'>ongoing</span>
<a href="/ongoing/misc/Colophon">publishing software</a> to get things
right.
The background music is from
<a href="http://magnatune.com/artists/dac_crowell">DAC Crowell</a>, whom I
recommend highly.</p>
<p>Now, it could have been done a lot better and there’s a big slippery slope
of sound capture and mixing and enhancing tools waiting for the unwary,
but the easiest possible way turns out to be good enough.</p>
<p>When there’s something that produces an effect this dramatic, and with a
barrier to entry this low, chances are somebody’s going to figure out how to
make something happen with it.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Syndication</cat>
<title>CNN Does RSS</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Via
<a href="http://www.paulbeard.org/wordpress/index.php?p=2430">Paul Beard</a>,
I hear that CNN has launched some RSS feeds.  They seem to work. 
<i>[Update: A nice person at CNN (whom I’d name except for he says “I have
enough to do 
without risking becoming the Internet face of CNN”) writes me to say the full
list of RSS feeds is now available
<a href="http://www.cnn.com/services/rss/">here</a>.]</i></p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Syndication</cat>
<title>A Wider Hosepipe</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>For those of us who just can’t be up-to-the-minute enough
on what the Net’s saying, a new goodie: Technorati’s “keyword watchlists”.
Get the
<a href="http://www.sifry.com/alerts/archives/000267.html">details</a> from
Dave Sifry.
I tried it, it seems to work.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/XML</cat>
<title>XTech, Time to Pitch In</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>This is the
<a href="http://www.xtech-conference.org">big European summer XML event</a>;
the
<a href="http://www.xtech-conference.org/2005/call.asp">call for papers</a> is
closing in a couple days.  Edd Dumbill, the chair, 
tells me that the submissions are excellent on the server side but there’s
room on the
<a href="http://usefulinc.com/edd/blog/contents/2004/12/20-browsers/read">client
side</a>, so all you XULoids and .NET-hacks and SVGers and XFormlings, get with
it.  
Lauren and I are going to try to go (haven’t been to Amsterdam in ages); I’m
particularly interested by the
<a href="http://usefulinc.com/edd/blog/contents/2005/01/05-xtech-open-data/read">Open
Data track</a>, which sounds like something new in the world.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Journalism</cat>
<title>Go Dan Go</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>That Dan Gillmor, he’s gone indie and so far it’s been good for him; 
swinging mightily with the truthstick, on successive days he’s scored
stinging blows on two guys named
<a href="http://dangillmor.typepad.com/dan_gillmor_on_grassroots/2005/01/arrogance_at_ap.html">Jobs</a>
and
<a href="http://dangillmor.typepad.com/dan_gillmor_on_grassroots/2005/01/truth_and_bill_.html">Gates</a>.
Sample sentence: <i>The purity of this lie is remarkable.</i>
Yep, looks like <span class='o'>ongoing</span> can happily outsource its
castigating-personal-computer-company-CEO operations to Mr. Gillmor.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Business/Open Source</cat>
<cat>Technology/XML</cat>
<title>Office Doc Format News</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>A couple of low-key news items 
in the Office Document XML space, worth highlighting because
I think this area is significant, as do
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2004/09/24/SmartEC">some important people</a>.
First off, the people standardizing this stuff over at OASIS (and soon, ISO)
<a href="http://xml.coverpages.org/ni2005-01-04-a.html">published a second
draft</a>, and, without any fanfare, they changed the name from
“OpenOffice.org XML Format” to “OpenDocument”, which is shorter, better, and
not tied to any particular implementation.
There’s action on the Microsoft front too; check the
<a href="http://groups-beta.google.com/group/microsoft.public.office.xml">microsoft.public.office.xml</a>
and
<a href="http://groups-beta.google.com/group/microsoft.public.xml">microsoft.public.xml</a>
newsgroups, where there are flurries of questions digging through the knotty
corners of WordML and ExcelML; you never really understand a dialect until
you have to write a program to generate it.
I’m sure the details will come out despite 
<a href="http://groups-beta.google.com/group/microsoft.public.xml/browse_thread/thread/ec47626088c12962/128957c5fb99646d">some
current irritation</a>, but this is a reason why Microsoft should cast a
friendly eye at the boring, bureaucratic, painful standardization process.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Publishing</cat>
<title>P@’s Snakeskin</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Check out Pat Chanezon on
<a href="http://blogs.sun.com/roller/page/pat/20050106#this_snake_skin_weblog_symbolizes">how
to communicate</a> in business.
The issue seems central and the problems aren’t solved.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology</cat>
<title>Bye, NCD</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Via the Reg, I see NCD
<a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2004/12/13/ncd_memo/">is</a> going 
<a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2005/01/07/ncd_closes_ops/">away</a>.
Kind of sad; I feel I have a personal relationship with the company.
I saw their first product at a 1989 Usenix and liked it enough to buy it and
<a href="http://groups-beta.google.com/group/comp.windows.x/browse_thread/thread/c8606f5e1b932f46/1ba0511b452e344a">posted
a review</a> which generated storms of email and Usenet traffic and many
thank-yous from NCD and, I immodestly think, significantly helped get them
launched.
Obviously, our 
<a href="http://www.sun.com/sunray">Sun Ray</a> is a direct descendant of the
original NCD idea, and the people here who use ’em generally love ’em.
I think it’s the nifty Java Card trick that makes them fly; go anywhere, plug
in the card, and there’s your desktop.
The notion, in an enterprise of any size, that you should have
independently managed standalone computers, one per person,
is obviously nuts.  There are some job functions and personality
types that call for a real computer of one’s own, but to the extent we can
avoid that, business is going to run smoother.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Publishing</cat>
<title>TechWikiDoc</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Jon Udell 
<a href="http://www.infoworld.com/article/05/01/07/02OPstrategic_1.html">suggests</a>
a new documentation strategy for 
technology vendors; rather than going on publishing incomplete, out-of-date,
poorly written manuals, they could just set up a per-product Wiki and let
the customer base fill it up with problems, fixes, workarounds, tips &amp;
tricks.
As he points out, most of us have gotten used to searching the Web for user
reports, rather than cracking product docs, to help us solve problems.
He suggests doing it at the Wikipedia, but I don’t think it matters that much
where the thing lives.
Like many great ideas, it’s obvious once you think of it.  I’m quite sure
it’ll happen.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>What/The World/Cats</cat>
<title>F.C., Triple-Daffodil Edition</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>These ones are adorable, I tell ya, adorable.</p>
<img src="0887.jpg" alt="Black long-haired cat with yellow daffodils" />
<img src="0888.jpg" alt="Black long-haired cat with yellow daffodils" />
<img src="0889.jpg" alt="Black long-haired cat with yellow daffodils" />
<p>This cat, Wolfgang Amadeus a.k.a. Wolfie, has
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2003/11/27/OnTime">appeared before</a> in 
<span class='o'>ongoing</span>; he died last century, unfortunately.
These are slides from the Eighties, digital fruits of
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2003/03/27/Scanner">the mighty Nikon</a>.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/XML</cat>
<title>Fast (They Say) and Open</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>There are a lot of people at Sun who are convinced that some sort of
binary XML representation is a good idea.
I’ve never been convinced, but they’re serious; they’ve
drafted a proposal and are working on getting it standardized; informally it’s
called the “Fast Infoset” and officially it’s
“ITU-T Rec. X.891 | ISO/IEC 24824-1”.
I’ve been particularly dubious because it’s built on ASN.1, which
I’ve had bad experiences with.
But those mostly had to do with broken or unavailable software, and that
objection may be moot, because as Eduardo Pelegri-Llopart
<a href="http://weblogs.java.net/blog/pelegri/archive/2005/01/start_using_bin.html">writes</a>,
they’re shipping an Open Source implementation.
Eduardo also tells me they’re getting lots of interest from outside of Sun.
Hey, as long as whenever someone tells me “I interchange XML” that means
they’re willing to interchange streams of Unicode characters with angle
brackets, I’m OK.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Mac OS X/Gripes</cat>
<title>Jeremy and Keystrokes</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>I see that Jeremy Zawodny has
<a href="http://jeremy.zawodny.com/blog/archives/003868.html">switched away
from Mac</a>, at least partially.
One of his reasons is also my #1 gripe with OS X, the primitive
keyboard access to application functions.  Windows and modern Linuxes both do
a much better job of this than OS X.
Apple refuses to worry about this because, they say,
<a href="http://asktog.com/TOI/toi06KeyboardVMouse1.html">we’ve done the
research</a> and it shows that you pitiful peasants just <em>think</em>
keyboarding is faster, mousing is faster and we can prove it.
I personally don’t believe it.  When I, for example, want to flip a photo 90°
right (or left), it is quicker in PaintShop Pro to hit CTL-R, R (or L),
Enter (and if I’m flipping it the same way as last time, I can skip the R/L)
than it is in PhotoShop to grab the mouse and go through two levels of
cascading menus. 
Since I
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2003/04/20/AnotherKey">persist in believing this</a>, am I a jungle-drumming anti-scientific
primitive?  
Well, once I tried to track down the experimental evidence, only it
doesn’t seem to be online, and the one time I found an abstract (this morning
I looked again and couldn’t find even that), it said something about measuring
the 
responses of “a variety of users across a variety of operations”.  Well, I
don’t give a flying flapdoodle about a variety of users and a variety of
operations; I care about the things that I do all the time, and by
definition, <strong>I am an expert</strong> at the things I do all the time,
and every time Apple makes me reach for the mouse, I swear.
I work for a company that would really like me to switch to
<a href="http://www.sun.com/software/javadesktopsystem/">another desktop</a>
<i>[Update: or maybe
<a href="http://blogs.sun.com/roller/page/timf/20050109#solaris_on_the_desktop">this</a>]</i>,
and if I do, this persistent stupidity about keystrokes will probably be the #1
cause.
<i>[To all the helpful people who’ve written me about OS X’s “Full Keyboard
Access”, thank you, I know about it, compared to the state of the art on
Windows and Linux it’s a toy.]</i></p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Arts/Photos</cat>
<title>Photointegrity Again</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Anyone who, like me, 
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2004/03/15/Photointegrity">worries about</a>
the relationship between photography and truth, should take the time to read 
<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/09/weekinreview/09bott.html?ex=1263013200&amp;en=387ef0f13bcd0d6a&amp;ei=5090&amp;partner=rssuserland">this
</a> <cite>New York Times</cite> piece on the subject.
<i>[Update: What was I thinking?
I neglected to mention probably the most thoughtful writing ever on this
subject, which was of course 
by Susan Sontag; some is online
<a href="http://www.newyorker.com/archive/content/?050110fr_archive04">here</a>
and
<a href="http://www.susansontag.com/onphotographyexcrpt.htm">here</a>.]</i></p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Syndication</cat>
<title>How Many Percent?</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Via Brent Simmons’
<a href="http://ranchero.com/2005/01/10.php">Ranchero</a>, some
<a href="http://www.burningdoor.com/feedburner/archives/000961.html">RSS
traffic stats</a> from FeedBurner, including the surprising claim that RSS
circulation is growing by 1% every weekday.
Herewith numbers from <span class='o'>ongoing</span>; lower but
interesting.</p>
<img src="FeedFetches.png" alt="Graph of RSS feed fetches from ongoing" />
<p>The data is from 2004.
Growth from 121 thousand to 258 thousand over the course of a year is not too
bad, but averaged out, it represents 1.6568%/week.
Which is not that great.
The variation is more than a little weird.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>The World/Space</cat>
<title>Cosmic Mystery Unscrewed</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>NASA is puzzled, but I think the solution is obvious.</p>
<img src="Iapetus.png" alt="Iapetus, by Cassini" />
<p>This is a picture of the
<a href="http://saturn.jpl.nasa.gov/news/press-release-details.cfm?newsID=526">mysterious
ridge</a> encircling Saturn’s moon Iapetus.
Look guys, you grab the top half with one hand and the bottom half with the
other and unscrew it.
Inside you will find the Solar System’s largest chunk of
<a href="http://www.sillyputty.com/">Silly Putty</a>.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Business/Intellectual Property</cat>
<title>Those IBM Patents</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Courtesy of ZDNet’s (very good)
<a href="http://blogs.zdnet.com/open-source/">Open source blog</a>,
a list of 
<a href="http://www.ibm.com/ibm/licensing/patents/pledgedpatents.pdf">those
patents</a> IBM is releasing sans charge.
But what does it mean?</p>
<p>I frankly have no idea, but here’s some context.
As of this writing, IBM
<a href="http://www.ibm.com/ibm/licensing/patents/portfolio.shtml">says</a>
that its “current active portfolio” contains about 23,000 patents, and that
in 2003 they received 3,415 new ones.</p>
<p>Patents aren’t free.
If you’re paying the retail rate to a decent law firm, one will cost you
in the range of US$10,000.  IBM should get economies of scale and not be
paying external law firms, but they’re spending at least $17M/year on this
stuff (just the lawyers, not the inventors).</p>
<p>So, this announcement means that IBM is unlocking 2.17% of their active
portfolio, representing a few million bucks in legal expenses.
At one level this is good; I mean, you have to be worried about
the legal overhang from
<i>US5694597: Method and system for optimizing access to a datastore</i>, or
<i>US5255387: Method and apparatus for concurrency control of shared data
updates and queries</i>, or <i>US6202098: Method and system for object
oriented notification</i> (to pick three completely at random from the page
I happened to have open).</p>
<p>But one is left with some questions: How were these selected?
Among the remaining 22,500 patents, are there some that IBM plans to begin
litigating?  Or probably won’t litigate, but might?  Or is this a general
statement that IBM will not bring its patent portfolio to bear against Open
Source software in general?
Inquiring minds want to know.</p>
<p>Oh yes, and a perusal of these patent titles would tend to reinforce the
cynical view that most software patents are complete unadulterated
bullshit.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Mac OS X</cat>
<title>Mini for Mom?</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>So is the Mini a game-changer? 
That question is too big.
But here’s an easier one: is it a good computer to buy
for my Mom?
<i>[Updated: Lots of feedback on what’s good for Mom, and on
appropriateness.]</i></p>
<img src="JeanBray.jpg" class="inline" alt="Jean Bray" />
<p>Jump <a href="#p-1">here</a> for the updates.</p>
<p>My mother is young and healthy enough that she’ll be needing a computer
for another decade or two for sure, and her 2000-vintage E-Machines Win98 box
is Just Not Gonna Cut It.
Especially now that she’s got broadband.</p>
<p>She’s got a perfectly good screen and printer and mouse, although her
keyboard’s kind of past it.  Plus she got a brand-new digicam at Christmas.
So on the surface, it would appear that the Mini might be a good
candidate.</p>
<p>Let’s go cost this out.
1.25 GHz and 512M ought to be fine, and we might as well spring the extra
pennies for the 80G drive, which will for her purposes be infinitely large.
So, if we add the Apple keyboard/mouse, it comes to $682.00, which is
not too bad at all.</p>
<img class="inline" src="MacMini.png" alt="Mac Mini" />
<p>Except for that’s not quite the whole story... Mom needs Office.
I don’t think the new iWork will help (no spreadsheet, to start
with) and much and all as I like
<a href="http://www.planamesa.com/neojava/en/index.php">NeoOffice/J</a>, I
don’t think it’s quite at ask-your-Mom-to-use-it level yet.
She has a horrible old copy of Office 97 that is of perhaps dubious
provenance (she says she doesn’t know where it came from, and I didn’t pay
for it), so I guess upgrades are out, and I see that Office for the Mac is
(gasp) $399.95!
Which frosts my socks, because this was supposed to be at least partly about
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2004/06/30/WorldHQ">C-$2MS</a>.
Mom is an active student and takes all sorts of courses through the
senior-citizens’ centre, but I bet that doesn’t qualify her for the $149.95
“Student and Teacher” edition.</p>
<p>I feel a slogan coming on: <strong>Microsoft is mean to little old
ladies!</strong> Not bad, eh?
Seriously, they should consider a senior-citizens discount, every museum and
concert hall and public-transit system in the world has one.</p>
<p>As for the hardware, people have pointed out that if you stay in the Wintel
world, you can get a little more for a little less.
But then we’d have more or less the same
Office problem over there.</p>
<p>The other option, then would be JDS or Knoppix or whatever; I suspect Mom
would do just fine with OpenOffice, but there might be a psychological
barrier as she had a bad experience with a much earlier version.</p>
<p>Speaking of psychological barriers; Mom’s a super-smart person and youthful
for her age, but is it fair to ask her to learn a whole new user interface?
She’s still prone to grumbling about how some of the things that she was used
to in Windows 3.1 don’t work any more.
My intuition is that the total irritation from having to use Windows into the
grave will be noticeably greater than the one-time irritation of learning OS
X.
So on balance, I suspect that there’s a Mini in Mom’s future. 
But if we end up paying the full ticket for Office, you can count on 
reading some irritated prose here.</p>
<h2 id='p-1'>Follow-Up</h2>
<p>First of all, it turns out that the Student and Teacher edition is
probably an available choice; my appallingly-cynical readership scoffed at the
<a href="http://www.microsoft.com/office/editions/prodinfo/students/doyouqualify.mspx">letter
of the law</a>.  I quote (name
withheld to protect the guilty): “Microsoft expects that everybody’s gonna
buy one of those for their three computers at home, they know business can’t
get away with it so this gets them in the door, residentially.”
Hmph.</p>
<p>Second, Simon Phipps
<a href="http://www.webmink.net/2005/01/playground-kids.htm">reports</a> that
his Mum does just fine with NeoOffice/J, maybe I’m being too pessimistic.</p>
<p>The interesting debate was with my brother Rob Bray, her other sysadmin,
and the source of her (perfectly legal, as it turns out) copy of Office 97.
He contended strongly that Mom should stay in Windows-land because that’s
the mainstream option and she’d have the maximum interop and minimum friction
with her peers.</p>
<p>Aren’t children awful?  Here we were arguing away without even asking Mom.
Eventually we were polite enough to invite her into the conversation:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Tim: “Rob's all mad at me.  In a friendly way.  He thinks it's madness to
consider anything but Windows, because that's what all your friends will be
using.”</p>
<p>Mom: “Not all of them, some of the people at the Centre have Apples and
have had for years. And most people are fairly irritated with Microsoft, and
if someone else started praising a new system, you never know what might
happen. Contrary to traditional belief, seniors are experimenters and like to
try new things. We even vote NDP, not all conservative or liberal.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So, there you go.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Journalism</cat>
<title>Read Governor</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>James Governor that is, whose 
<a href="http://www.redmonk.com/jgovernor/">space online</a> has been
consistently strong.
He’s a must-read for Sun people because he frequently holds forth on what we
should and shouldn’t be doing, but I think anyone interested in our
profession would find a subscription worth the investment of time.
Just at the moment on the front page are strong pieces on
<a href="http://www.redmonk.com/jgovernor/archives/000389.html">Rexx</a>,
<a href="http://www.redmonk.com/jgovernor/archives/000388.html">Linux
safety</a>, and 
<a href="http://www.redmonk.com/jgovernor/archives/000380.html">visualizing
Amazon Web Services</a>.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Journalism</cat>
<title>Journo Burn</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>I’ve just been burned by a journalist for the first time in years, and I
really don’t like the feeling.  I’ve been doing this a long time, and I’ve
gotten to know a lot of the writers in this field, and often I’ll get emails
out of the blue saying “What do you think about XXX” and unless it’s
violently controversial or dangerous, I’ll tell them, and by and large
they’re smart and insightful and honest</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>The World/Places/Vancouver</cat>
<cat>The World/Life Online/People</cat>
<title>Michael Klassen</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>This gentleman has just launched a kind-of-Vancouverish kind-of-Canadian
kind-of-pop-cultural
<a href="http://www.michaelklassen.ca/">online presence</a>, which looks
pretty good so far; a little more weight on the top left corner of the
blogosphere can’t hurt.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Arts/Photos</cat>
<cat>Technology/Software</cat>
<title>PhotoShop Elements 3 Review</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Skipping to the conclusion: It’s good, if you’re using Elements already go
upgrade. 
But along the way, there 
are thoughts on software’s lifespan and  pricing.
Plus, a thin black woman kissing a flower taller than herself.</p>
<img src="1144.jpg" alt="A tetrahedron-shaped lamp and flower arrangements on a dark wood surface" />
<div class="caption"><p>On the dark wood chest are a tetrahedron-shaped lamp
and some flower arrangements.</p></div>
<h2 id='p-1'>The Main Thing</h2>
<p>Elements 3—the Mac version at least—is faster; much faster.
The illustrations in this piece are
<a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/200x/2003/03/27/Scanner">slide scans</a>, and quite
large; the one 
above is 4739x3285, 8.45M on disk.
On E2, they were painfully slow to load and save, and now they’re pretty
snappy; at least twice as fast.
The various filtering and cropping operations don’t feel any faster, which is
fine because they were pretty well OK before.  
But that loading and saving has really juiced up my workflow.</p>
<h2 id='p-2'>Little Pros and Cons</h2>
<p>The level of fit &amp; finish is just generally better, everything’s a
little slicker and a little smoother.
They’ve reorganized the screen layout and well, whatever, there are a few
more pixels of photospace available in among the tools, which is good.</p>
<img src="1167.jpg" alt="Two african figurines and flower arrangement" />
<div class="caption"><p>Two African figurines keep the flowers company.</p></div>
<p>There are a bunch of little changes in keystrokes and layouts and
selection behavior, some of which help and others don’t.  Whatever.
The new “Healing Brush” tool is pretty neat.</p>
<p>There are some stability issues, I’ve already had a couple of crashes when
loading and saving these big-ass slide scans.</p>
<p>It’s still stupidly lacking in keyboard shortcuts, but hey, 
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2005/01/09/JeremyOut">Apple has proved that doesn’t matter</a>.</p>
<p>On balance, anyone who’s using Elements already should totally upgrade,
and anyone who’s shopping for photogeek software a step up from iPhoto, this
is a pretty good option.</p>
<img src="1163.jpg" alt="African figurine, flower arrangement" />
<div class="caption"><p>The Kiss.</p></div>
<p>Plus, the price is right.</p>
<h2 id='p-3'>Software Pricing</h2>
<p>Via Amazon.ca, Elements 3 cost me C$107.99, which is to say C$128.75
all-in with shipping and taxes.
Which is an interesting price-point, and leads me to another new-year
prediction: 2005 is going to be a pivotal year for software pricing.
<i>Item</i>: Joel Spolsky’s must-read
<a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/CamelsandRubberDuckies.html">Camels
and Rubber Duckies</a>, a touch over-long perhaps but stuffed with
highly-compressed wisdom on the subject.
<i>Item:</i> We ship Solaris 10 for free, with the expectation of huge
financial upside.
<i>Item:</i> Bryan Cantrill’s
<a href="http://blogs.sun.com/bmc/20040828#the_economics_of_software">The
Economics of Software</a>; if you don’t know what “The FYO Point” is, read
this one.
<i>Item:</i> Finally, James Governor’s
<a href="http://www.redmonk.com/jgovernor/archives/000378.html">eloquent
bafflement</a> at the notion that Sun’s per-employee pricing is
“confusing”.</p> 
<img src="1174.jpg" alt="African figures, flower arrangement and swagger stick" />
<div class="caption"><p>There’s another African artifact there, a sort of swagger stick.
Consider the texture of the walls.</p></div>
<h2 id='p-4'>The Old New Thing</h2>
<p>While we may be entering a new era in software pricing, we’re not entering
an era of new software.
Remember Photoshop Elements, how we got started on this ramble? 
It’s basically good ol’ PhotoShop stripped down a bit, and that’s in release,
what, three hundred and twelve?
And let’s look at some other recent high-impact software releases: Solaris
10, Linux 2.6 (which means, more or less, 5), Oracle 10<i>g</i>, Windows XP
(which identifies itself to a Web server as “Windows NT 5.1”), Office 2003
(internally called “Office 11”), Mac OS X 10.3 (which is in large part
Darwin, which is in large part *bsd release, uh, some big number).
Not one of these pieces of software is under ten years old.</p>
<p>The lesson is this: want to have high impact in the software world?
Go to work on something big, old, and well-established; make it
better.</p>
<p><i>[Flower arrangements (and photos, maybe) by Cath Bray.]</i></p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>The World/Places/Vancouver</cat>
<cat>Arts/Photos</cat>
<title>Wintry</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Last week, we had one of our rare Vancouver snowstorms. 
But the stuff’s still on the ground.</p>
<p>The day of a snowfall here, people are cheery and fatalistic about it; the
city’s not set up for it, but it doesn’t happen very
often and it’s a novelty.
The snow stacks up bright on the apples that neglected to leave the tree.</p>
<img src="IMGP1367.jpg" alt="Fresh snow falling on apples in the tree" />
<p>The children run wild in a universe entirely occupied by snowballs, sleds,
snow forts, and of course snow people.
I thought our jaunty specimen was shaped more like a snow lady, but
5&#xbd;-year-olds are traditionalists and he wouldn’t have it.</p>
<img src="Snowman.jpg" alt="Snowman" />
<p>The Christmas lights, which should be down by now but I’m not climbing
ladders until it gets 10° warmer, are warm in the dusky white.</p>
<img src="IMGP1379.jpg" alt="Christmas lights in snow" />
<p>But like I said, that was last week.
The snow is hard and icy and dirty now, like in some big city back East, and
we remember how one winter back there, five months in, we decided to move
three time-zones West to get away from this shit.</p>
<p>It’s getting us all down, even the snowman.</p>
<img src="IMG_3180.jpg" alt="Melting snowman" />
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Web/Services</cat>
<cat>Arts/Books</cat>
<title>Real World Web Services</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>This is an
<a href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/realwws/">O’Reilly book</a> by Will
Iverson, whom I don’t know.
Given my
<a href="/ongoing/What/Technology/Web/Services/">frequent public
grumbling</a> on the subject, I thought I should give it a serious look.</p>
<p>The title could have been <cite>Practical Web Services</cite> and been
just as accurate; this book is blessedly free of
<a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000018.html">architecture
astronautics</a>.
It devotes almost no space to theory or models or
<a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/webservices/understanding/specs/default.aspx">specifications
maps</a>, but it has actual code-complete Web-Services apps
which talk to Amazon, EBay, Google, FedEx, PayPal, CDDB, Blogger, and
LiveJournal, often several at once.
The nearest it gets to theory is crash introductions to Apache’s Tomcat,
XML-RPC, and Axis, plus the Quartz scheduler, plus RSS.
All the implementations are Java, in particular there’s quite a bit of JSP.</p>
<p>It has a frankly dismissive closing <cite>Future Web Services
Directions</cite> chapter, which seems about right to me.
Money quote, which does not 100% reflect my world-view but is worth
reproducing: <i>Unfortunately, if the examples as shown in this book are any
indication, REST-based projects are liable to lead to considerably more
client code for the maintenance of the XML processing as compared to
SOAP-based solutions.</i></p>
<p>People who care about Web Services in the wild should check this one out.
And so, especially, should WS-Architecture-Astronauts.</p>
<p><i>[Disclosure: O’Reilly sends me notifications of new releases, and when
I ask for them, I get the books free.]</i></p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Arts/Books</cat>
<title>Strange &amp; Norrell</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>That would be
<a href="http://www.jonathanstrange.com/">Jonathan Strange &amp; Mr
Norrell</a> by Susanna Clarke, an immensely large novel whose stylish
white-on-black and black-on-white covers are occupying miles of shelf-space
everywhere.
Summary: it’s a good book.
Herewith notes plus ramblings on travel and reading.</p>
<h2 id='p-1'>Gaming Heathrow</h2>
<p>What happened was, I came home from
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2004/12/16/Javapolis">Antwerp</a> via Brussels and
London.
Northern Europe’s weather was bad and the air schedules were hurting; the
flight to Heathrow was delayed.
Bearing my tight connection to Vancouver in mind, I decided to check my rollie
as luggage, although it’s perfectly legal in the cabin.
(This caused a little difficulty after I Christmas-shopped in Brussels
airport and staggered onto the plane festooned with shopping bags 
like a mall victim).</p>
<p>Anyhow, Heathrow, as usual, was congested and slow and
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2003/11/01/HeathrowSucks">generally sucked</a>,
and by the time I finally got to the Air Canada desk, the fellow shook his
head doubtfully: “I’m afraid you are rather late, sir.”  
I smiled sweetly and said “I do have checked luggage,” knowing full well that
it would have transited Heathrow much faster than I and be secure in the
plane’s hold.
He looked pained and reached for his phone to call the gate.
In this era of terrorism, no plane can fly without a passenger in the cabin
belonging to each and every bag in the belly.
And they really don’t want to unpack the hold to find that one unaccompanied
Samsonite.</p> 
<p>As I finally got into the terminal, the big voice in the rafters was
intoning “Will Mr. Bray please proceed now to Gate 389.”
But I had a problem; I’d realized that I’d read everything in my carry-on
and was about to get on a 10-hour flight <i>sans</i> pages to turn.
Unthinkable.
But hey, I had a bag in the plane, so I stopped by the bookshop (Heathrow’s
one redeeming feature) and that’s how I got this book (and read the first
two-thirds of it).</p>
<h2 id='p-2'>Strange &amp; Norrell</h2>
<p>The best thing about this book is the plot and pace; it lopes right along,
really never failing to be entertaining.
Some have complained about the idiosyncratic deployment of Jane Austen
spelling; I don’t think it helps much but it doesn’t get in the way either.
The people in it are largely interesting and most are nicely fleshed out,
with only a few spear-carriers.
The cameos from famous historical personages—Wellington, Byron (especially),
the mad King George—are good fun, and the locations—here and there in
Britain, Spain in the peninsular war, Venice—have lots of colour and feel
historically authentic.
The reviews say it’s full of literary references, but I only spotted a
couple so I guess I’m not literate enough.</p>
<p>The two protagonists, named in the title, English magicians both, are
twitchily obsessive about their work in a way computer geeks will find
familiar and comforting.
And the magic itself is really very good; a plausible presentation of what
real magic in the real world might be like, should such a thing exist.</p>
<p>One gripe; our authoress’ cast of characters is very male-heavy; the women
who appear do so mostly as hapless victims of magic, pawns at best on the
board. 
I would beg Ms Clarke, in her heavily-prefigured sequel, to include one or
two interesting members of her own gender.</p>
<p>But on balance I think this is a good story well told, and most people
would like it.</p>
<h2 id='p-3'>Reading in General</h2>
<p>I’m going through a lot fewer books these days; the problem is that the
combination of RSS, wireless, and
<a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/">decent on-screen typography</a> has
made it terribly convenient to read the world in real time, instead of reading
books, and the world is telling an interesting story, almost always.
It’s hard for authors to compete.</p>
<p>But I think I’ve swung too far away from books toward the world, and am
going to make a conscious effort to swing back a bit.</p>
<p>I’ll say one thing though; text presented in ink on paper is a
highly-advanced technology, better than what you can get from a computer
screen.
Within certain limitations; although <cite>Strange &amp; Norrell</cite> is
elegantly typeset in Baskerville with generous leading, its 782 pages make it
awkwardly large, thick, and heavy.
Something lightweight and electronic would be a lot easier on the wrists.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Publishing</cat>
<title>Group Blogs?</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>We’re out there talking to people about Enterprise Blogging, and one of
the things we keep hearing is “We want to do group blogs.”
Well, the customer is always right, so groupblogging is looming larger and
larger in the
<a href="http://www.rollerweblogger.org/page/project">Roller</a> to-do list.
I’m surprised and unconvinced; out there in the world, group blogs are the
exception rather than the rule.
I suspect that there may be some excess caution at work; people a bit
reluctant to start talking to the world feeling that doing it in a group
context will be somehow less exposed.
On this one, I’d advise going with the flow, and the flow today is mostly
about individual voices.
But I learned long ago not to tell people what they should and
shouldn’t want to do with technology.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Publishing</cat>
<title>Referrer Spamstorm</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Near as I can tell, pretty well every somewhat-visible website in the
world is seeing its logfiles fill up with with bogus page fetches there only
as a vehicle for a spammish “referrer” field; whether or not the site posts
referrer data.
This high-volume flood is a fairly recent phenomenon, and what makes it weird
is that the vast majority of the bogus referrer sites are off the air due to
some terms-of-service violation.
It would appear that a sleazebag somewhere launched a really ambitious
assault on the whole 
world—using, I can only assume, a few zillion zombified drone machines—only
to be found out and have their hosting yanked while their mindless slaves
continue to spew vacuous venom into logfiles everywhere.
Damn, the Internet is a weird place.
<i>[Update: This was a big one, and lots of people studied it.]
[Update: I think I may have spoken with the perp.]</i></p>
<p>John Sinteur
<a href="http://wordpress.org/support/topic.php?id=20956#post-119138">traces</a> the
bad buy back to a single IP address.
Arve Bersvendsen 
<a href="http://virtuelvis.com/archives/2005/01/referer_spammers_are_comment_spammers_too">offers</a>
more research.
And
<a href="http://www.annelisabeth.com/blog/archives/000165.html">Anne
Elisabeth</a> discovers that those off-the-air sites aren’t staying that
way.</p>
<p>For a while this morning, it seemed to have stopped. 
But as of 11:30 AM Pacific time, they’re back.
This is big and involves a lot of domain names and a well-known IP
address; wouldn’t be nice if some capable law-enforcement organization found
whoever it is that’s doing it and THREW THEIR ASS IN JAIL?</p>
<p>So I did a whois on one of the domain names that shows up, and there’s a
listing there, with people’s names and phone numbers, in New York.
I called the 212- phone number and a woman’s voice said “Hello?”
It dawned on me that the phone number could be another forgery, so I just said
“wrong number” and hung up.
Jeepers.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Business/Intellectual Property</cat>
<title>Two Licenses</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>There’s an interesting debate around syndication licensing going on,
<a href="http://trademark.blog.us/blog/2005/01/14.html">launched</a> by
Martin Schwimmer, with the important links aggregated by
Scoble (<a href="http://radio.weblogs.com/0001011/2005/01/15.html#a9204">here</a>,
<a href="http://radio.weblogs.com/0001011/2005/01/15.html#a9211">here</a>,
<a href="http://radio.weblogs.com/0001011/2005/01/16.html#a9213">here</a>).
I think the conclusion is obvious; some people, including me, need to have
different licenses for site and feed.</p>
<p>Schwimmer may not have a firm grasp of the issues, but he does have a
point; it’s reasonable to be concerned about Person A building a business
around Person B’s feed.</p>
<p>Reasonable to be concerned, I say; but not reasonable to try to stop 
happening.  At the end of the day it’s just nuts to 
try to fine-tune what other people do with your syndication feed.
Which is to say, if you’re putting your full content in your feed, I think
you’re pretty much giving it to the world.  Whether you want to or not, it’s
in the nature of the syndication beast. 
Not just RSS; Atom ain’t gonna change this.</p>
<p>Here at <span class='o'>ongoing</span>, quite a few fragments are not all
there in the feed; and none of the photos are.
For a variety of reasons, outside the scope of this debate, that’s not going
to change.
And whether or not I like what people do with my feed (I mean
<a href="http://www.livejournal.com/users/timbray/">this</a> seems kind of
lame, but harmless), I don’t see much point in trying to control it.</p>
<p>I don’t want others trying to cash in on my long essays and pictures
though, and I’ve already gone after people who are replicating the whole
thing, and I’ll do it again any time I see it happening.</p>
<p>The problem is, though, that what I’ve just said here is inconsistent with
what I say on
<a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/misc/Copyright">my copyright page</a>.
I think my
<a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/">Creative Commons
license</a> (Attribution-NonCommercial 2.0) arguably says you can’t reproduce
my feed for your own business purposes, i.e. do what Bloglines does.</p>
<p>It seems to me the right solution is obvious; rewrite things to apply a
Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike license to the syndication feeds,
while retaining Attribution-NonCommercial coverage for the full text and
photos; hmm, an initial read suggests I need separate licenses for text and
photos.</p>
<p>Or am I missing something obvious?
By the way,
<a href="http://www.laurenwood.org/anyway/">Lauren</a> pointed this out to me
months ago, but neither of us thought it was that big a deal.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Web</cat>
<title>No Follow</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>It’s nice to see that Google has
<a href="http://www.google.com/googleblog/2005/01/preventing-comment-spam.html">taken
up the cudgels</a> against comment spam in what seems like an effective way.
I can see another application: it allows me to express negative feelings
hypertextually without collateral Google-juice damage.
For example, the recent referrer-spam perps, who are
<a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.fidelityfunding.net">pathetic losers</a>, 
<a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.fidelityfunding.net">ineffectual morons</a>,
<a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.fidelityfunding.net">abusive predators</a>,
and probably
<a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.fidelityfunding.net">deserve to be in
jail</a>.
There, wasn’t that fun?
Which suggests an enhancement: <code>rel="justlabel"</code>, which says “don’t
count this link for ranking purposes, but do take its content seriously
as relevant to the indicated site.”</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Syndication</cat>
<cat>Technology/Metadata</cat>
<title>What Do Tags Mean?</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>I’m almost convinced that this new
<a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/">Technorati Tags</a> thing is
important, but I’m 100% convinced that I don’t understand where it’s going or
what the implications are.
Which is OK, because I suspect nobody else does either.</p>
<p>It took only a few minutes’ hacking to add them to the RSS feed here at
<span class='o'>ongoing</span> (sigh, my Perl code, what with this and
<code>rel="nofollow"</code>, is up over 2,000 lines).
So, for some period of time starting a few minutes or hours after I publish
this, and probably lasting for a couple of weeks, this page should appear
<a href="http://www.technorati.com/tags/Technology/Metadata">here</a>, and
for a much shorter period of time
<a href="http://www.technorati.com/tags/Metadata">here</a>.</p>
<h2 id='p-5'>How-To</h2>
<p>There’s an embryonic
<a href="http://developers.technorati.com/wiki/RelTag">publishers’s
how-to</a>,
which tells you about putting the following in your pages:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;link rel="tag" href="http://technorati.com/tag/foo"/></code></pre>
<p>It turns out you can also just put
<code>&lt;dc:subject>foo&lt;/dc:subject></code> in your feed (assuming you’ve
declared the
<code>dc:</code> prefix properly) which is shorter and (much &amp; all as I
love Technorati) arguably more open.</p>
<p>Except for, as a 
<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/">Web-Architectural</a> kinda guy, I
like the idea of identifying categories with URIs.
Except for, the whole point of that is that everyone can have their own, and
Technorati’s setup only recognizes the ones beginning
<code>http://technorati.com/</code>. 
Except for, the more the tags gets shared, the more useful they are.
Hmm, more thought required.
Dave Sifry, who launched this whole episode, has published his thoughts
<a href="http://www.sifry.com/alerts/archives/000270.html">here</a>.</p>
<h2 id='p-4'>Feed or Page?</h2>
<p>It’s interesting that if you use the <code>&lt;link></code> technique your
tags are in your page, but if you use <code>&lt;dc:subject></code>, they’re
in your feed.
Given the fact that a lot of pages are still tag-soup, while the vast
majority of feeds are reasonably well-formed, the feed feels like a more
natural home for this kind of metadata; but it’s nice that both options are
available.</p>
<h2 id='p-1'>On Metadata</h2>
<p>I’ve spent a lot of time thinking about metadata and have
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2003/07/29/SearchMeta">written on the subject</a>;
the most important conclusion was: <em>There is no cheap metadata.</em>
I haven’t seen anything to make me change my mind.</p>
<p>For a different, and very fresh, spin on the same proposition, see Clay
Shirky’s
<a href="http://www.corante.com/many/archives/2005/01/07/folksonomies_controlled_vocabularies.php">folksonomies
+ controlled vocabularies</a>.
He takes on the question of whether “folksonomies”, such as what may emerge
around Technorati Tags, are good enough.
It’s worth reading all of it, but this in particular seems to the point:</p>
<blockquote><p>This is something the ‘well-designed metadata’ crowd has never
understood — just because it’s better to have well-designed metadata along one
axis does not mean that it is better along all axes, and the axis of cost, in
particular, will trump any other advantage as it grows
larger. </p></blockquote>
<p>Having said that, and granting the proposition that The Simplest Thing
That Could Possibly Work usually wins, I still have to say that the
Technorati Tags all being in a single flat namespace does seem a
little, 
well, brittle.</p>
<h2 id='p-3'>On Atom</h2>
<p>Consider the Atom <code>category</code> element.
Here’s an example:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;category term="Vancouver" /></code></pre>
<p>Here’s another:</p>
<pre><code><![CDATA[<category scheme="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/What/" 
          term="Arts/Music/Performance">
Arts 
· Music 
· · Performance
</category>]]></code></pre>
<p>You see, Atom lets you express tags just as simple as the the current
Technorati style.
But if you want to say “here’s a tag (a string), here’s the vocabulary it comes
from (a URI), and here’s a human-readable version you can display”, Atom can
do that too.</p>
<p>I think that it would be nice if a huge number of web pages
converged on using a simple, flat, shared set of tags with entries like
<code>vancouver</code> and <code>mac os x</code> and <code>tsunami
relief</code>, which the current setup works well for.</p>
<p>But I think it would also be nice if, once we have Atom, there are feeds
about Petroleum Geology with their own tags, and feeds about
Military Training too, and they each have their own <code>drill</code>
tag.
Which Atom would support nicely.</p>
<p>Of course, the only people who would need to know about the Petroleum or
Military tags would be people specifically looking for that kind of
stuff; someone looking for a <code>drill</code> tag generically would
probably get both and maybe that would be fine.</p>
<p>Bottom line: I suspect Technorati, and anyone else who takes this up, should
offer an (optional) “scheme” field in their tag search capability, which
would be handy for those who care and invisible for those who don’t.</p>
<h2 id='p-2'>On Mechanics</h2>
<p>At <span class='o'>ongoing</span>, here’s what I’m doing: for this
fragment, which is in <code>Technology/Syndication</code> and
<code>Technology/Metadata</code>, the RSS feed will contain:</p>
<pre><code><![CDATA[<dc:subject>Technology/Syndication</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Technology</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Syndication</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Technology/Metadata</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>Metadata</dc:subject>]]></code></pre>
<p>I’d be surprised if Technorati is going to do anything very smart with the
hierarchy, but I don’t see any reason to lose information while generating
this stuff.</p>
<p>After I put the tags in my feed, I immediately started banging on
Technorati and was having trouble finding them there.
One reason was obvious: all the back items in my feed hadn’t changed even
though they now had <code>&lt;dc:subject></code> tags, and Technorati’s
change-detection algorithms detected that and refused to re-index.  Fair
enough.</p>
<p>Then, some still weren’t showing up, largely because they were sorted by
date not authority; anything older than a few days, in a popular tag, just
isn’t going to be there.</p>
<p>I’m pretty sure this is a bug: if I do a tag search for “Microsoft”, and
if Robert Scoble or Jonathan Schwartz have posted on the subject any time in
the last 48 hours, I want those at the top of the damn list, not what some
college kid wrote three hours ago.</p>
<p>Here are a few notes on how Technorati’s doing things right now.
First of all, they’re monocasing tags.
Second, they’re OK with spaces, for example
<a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/Mac+OS+X">here</a> is a tag search for
“Mac OS X”.
Third, they treat my full pathnames as standalone tags, as in
<a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/Technology/Metadata">Technology/Metadata</a>.
</p>
<h2 id='p-6'>The Questions</h2>
<p>What I’m left with, mostly, are questions:
Should I be using my own category tree, or
should I switch to tags that Technorati already knows about?
Should I introduce <code>Tim Bray</code> and <code>ongoing</code> tags,
presumably on all entries?
Should categories be in trees?
Should their names be monocased (with potential for i18n breakage)?
Are categories actually going to produce better searches than good old
full-text?  Here are
<a href="http://www.technorati.com/tag/Vancouver">tag</a> and
<a href="http://www.technorati.com/cosmos/search.html?rank=&amp;url=Vancouver">full-text</a>
searches for “Vancouver”; what do you think?
What am I doing categories for?
What is anybody doing categories for?
What is everybody doing categories for?
</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Technology/Coding</cat>
<title>Testing Backward</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>I just wasted some time by making a real dumb mistake in my unit testing
setup, and I think that when tech bloggers do this they should publish 
the details,
because wisdom is in large part the knowledge of how to avoid doing dumb
things, and thus grows globally as a function of the published inventory of
stupid mistakes.
Thus, herewith, a description of how you can waste time by 
doing your unit testing just slightly wrong.
<i>[Updated: A suggested best practice to avoid this.]
[And again.]</i></p>
<p>Scenario: you’re writing a class that has a real complex constructor, and
one that you’re pretty sure is going to be a performance bottleneck;
despite your best efforts to avoid premature optimization, you end up with an
80-line constructor including a couple of nested loops and a
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2003/03/22/Binary">binary search</a>.
The rest of the methods have names like <code>size()</code> and
<code>first()</code> and don’t do much.</p>
<p>Using your best XP/TDD style, you bang out <code>return null;</code> and
<code>return -1;</code> bodies for all the little methods, and dive into
getting that constructor right, and then you really bear down on some good
unit tests for it.</p>
<p>Sure enough, the first few runs blow up in <code>testConstructor()</code>
with null pointers and infinite loops and so on, you fix them feeling
virtuous, this how TDD is supposed to go, right?</p>
<p>After a while, it’s not instantly blowing up, but you can’t seem to get
your basic sanity-check tests to work, it seems that your constructor is
laboring mightily and producing nothing.
You end up single-stepping in the debugger, and sure enough, it sure looks
like the object is getting constructed.
But all the tests show it as empty.</p>
<p>At this point, you go elsewhere for coffee, except for walking down the
hall you say “Oh shit” out loud, because you suddenly remembered all those
<code>return null;</code> and <code>return -1;</code> stub methods that you
were going to get to later, and you’d used them in the Constructor test to
look at your object, hadn’t you?</p>
<h2 id='p-1'>How To Avoid This</h2>
<p>In another hemisphere, <a href="http://randomised.blogspot.com/">Tony
Fisk</a> shared a giggle at me around
<a href="http://www.invetech.com.au/">his workplace</a>, where a person named
Greg Presneill suggested: “Or, just throw a
<code>System.NotImplementedException</code> instead 
of arbitrary <code>return -1;</code> or <code>return null;</code> etc.”
That’s .NET-talk, the Java equivalent would be something like:</p>
<pre><code>throw new RuntimeException("Method not implemented");</code></pre>
<p>Obvious once you hear it, and immensely safer and better for stubs; I
assume lots of people are already doing it.</p>
<p>A ton of people, way too many to list, suggested using
<code>java.lang.UnsupportedOperationException</code>, which is a subclass of
<code>RuntimeException</code>.  Whatever, it doesn’t seem like that big a
deal.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>The World/Politics</cat>
<title>Inauguration Day</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>On this occasion, I’d like to wish our American neighbours the best of
luck over the next four years; and I think you’re going to need it.
I was one of the tiny percentage of non-Americans who thought invading Iraq
might be sane, but then I thought then and I think now that it’s not OK 
to start a war based on on a bunch of bald-faced lies and yes, 
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2004/07/09/IntelReport">they knew they were
lying</a>.
Now, everyone knows
<a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4169107.stm">the WMDs were never
there</a> (check out the
<a href="http://instapundit.com/archives/020470.php">desperate sniveling</a>
from the pro-administration camp).
I, like I suspect a large majority of the civilized world, really hope
that the Iraquis manage against the odds to pull off a decent election and end
up with some sort of a decent society, and that the US kids sweating it out
and dying in the desert manage to make it home alive.
Whatever you think about that, a majority of Americans disagreed with my
opinion that if the US were a business, it was time to 
<a href="/ongoing/When/200x/2004/10/14/Election2004 ">fire the boss</a>.
So, today, tens of millions get poured into the inauguration
ceremonies.
Meanwhile, bafflingly, it seems like
<a href="http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/archives/individual/2005_01/005443.php">they’re
doing it again</a> and once again, it seems to be
working. 
You couldn’t make this stuff up.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>The World/Humor</cat>
<cat>Technology/Publishing/Reference</cat>
<title>&#xcb;rüd&#xef;t&#xef;ön</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>There’s exhaustive research and scholarly publishing, and then there’s pop
culture, and sometimes they meet in 
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heavy_metal_umlaut">ëcstätïc
trïümph</a>.
Oh my goodness gracious, Jon Udell has built a wonderful monument of 
<a href="http://weblog.infoworld.com/udell/gems/umlaut.html">mëtä-schölärshïp</a>
on this base.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Business/Sun</cat>
<title>Analysts and Sex</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>On Wednesday, I spent a few hours at the
<a href="http://www.cplan.com/sunanalyst2005">Sun Analyst Summit</a>, which
was sure educational for me, so I hope the analysts got something out of it
too.</p>
<p>The idea is, we import a few hundred analysts for three days on-campus
at Sun.  They fall into two baskets: “Financial Analysts”, who want to
know whether they should recommend buying or selling SUNW, and
“Industry Analysts”, who advise anyone who’ll pay as to what’s hot and what’s
not in the computing business.
All of our execs were there to make their pitches, and I listened to some of
that by webcast.
The only thing that would have been new to a student of Sun was the
heavy focus on our 
<a href="http://www.sun.com/sungrid/">grid offerings</a>; which will be a
game-changer if they take off.</p>
<p>But there’s no point me telling you what we told the analysts, 
it’s their job to decide what’s important and distill that and pass it on.
So I’ll describe what they said to us, and I bet this the first
time one of these has been blogged from the company side.  (News Flash:
<em>All</em> of the analysts read blogs.)</p>
<p>My part in the show was small;
<a href="http://www.sun.com/aboutsun/media/ceo/mgt_papadopoulos.html">Greg
Papadopoulos</a> hosted a “CTO Panel” on which 
there were 11 of us:
<a href="http://www.sun.com/aboutsun/media/presskits/eservices/bios.html">Jim Baty</a>,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andy_Bechtolsheim">Andy
Bechtolsheim</a>, me,
<a href="http://research.sun.com/people/diffie/">Whit Diffie</a>, 
<a href="http://www.sun.com/aboutsun/media/bios/bios-fleischer.html">Balint
Fleischer</a>,
<a href="http://today.java.net/pub/au/189">Graham Hamilton</a>,
<a href="http://www.sun.com/aboutsun/media/bios/bios-marsland.html">Tim
Marsland</a>,
<a href="http://www.sun.com/aboutsun/media/bios/bios-splain.html">Mike Splain</a>, 
<a href="http://blogs.sun.com/roller/page/stern">Hal Stern</a>, and 
<a href="http://www.sun.com/aboutsun/media/bios/bios_tremblay.html">Marc Tremblay</a>.
We each took a minute to say what we thought was exciting, then the analysts
got to pop questions, every one of which was intelligent, to most of which we
had good 
answers; except for the first one.</p>
<img src="IMG_3239-2.jpg" alt="Audience at the 2005 Sun Analyst Summit" />
<h2 id='p-1'>The Hard Question</h2>
<p>A guy from Deloitte whose name I didn’t get put up his hand and asked (I
paraphrase) “Why am I looking at twelve middle-aged white guys?”</p>
<p>Ouch.</p>
<p>We have some defense on the “white” part of the question; another random
slice across senior Sun people could easily turn up a dozen none of
whose genes are out of the European pool.  Same for most high-tech companies I
know about.</p>
<p>But the gender thing hurts.  Obviously, it’s not just Sun; I get to sit in
a lot of rooms-full of senior people trying to do industry leadership,
whatever that means, and there are lots of times when there aren’t any women,
or just one or two, and <strong>THAT SUCKS</strong>.
Even if there weren’t the ethical issues, in case you hadn’t noticed we’re
still suffering from a general talent shortage in this business, and it’s not
very smart to only draw from half the population.</p>
<p>So Greg and the rest of us expressed pious hopes that in
another generation or so the picture would be a little more diverse, but
frankly I’ve never heard a real convincing explanation of what the root cause
is and what we can do about it.  Greg’s more optimistic than I am, and I hope
he’s right.</p>
<img src="IMG_3246.jpg" alt="World’s smallest secure web server, and a smart sensor" />
<div class="caption"><p>Greg showed these at dinner; the round thing is the
world’s smallest secure Web server, with HTTPS and elliptic cryptography
built in; the other is some sort of smart sensor with a radio and
accelerometer and other stuff, runs Java of course. The next rev will be way
smaller.</p></div>
<h2 id='p-2'>Other Questions</h2>
<p>There were lots of questions, most of them good; here are the ones that
stuck in my memory, some of them asked informally over dinner.</p>
<h3>How Long Are Your Time-Frames?</h3>
<p>The answers were all over the map.  The silicon guys are working on
products for delivery years and years out, while the Java-heads try to keep
their release cycle under two years.  I was the loser on this one; as a
Web-head I feel lucky if I can see three months ahead.</p>
<h3>Why Do You Do Java Anyhow?</h3>
<p>That questioner couldn’t see how it made us any money.
This has been addressed before by smarter people than me, but I will point
out that if Sun wasn’t doing Java, we probably wouldn’t be open for business
today.</p>
<h3>Why Doesn’t Sun Do a Database?</h3>
<p>Well, it would be nice to have one, but does the world need another?</p>
<h3>Does Jonathan Really Write His Own Blog?</h3>
<p>Yes.</p>
<h3>Are the Security Specialists Winning, Or Are the Hackers?</h3>
<p>You’ll notice Sun doesn’t get hacked much.
Whit thinks we’re gaining.</p>
<h3>Do the People Building the Web-Services Stack Know the Net Has Stochastic
Behavior?</h3>
<p>Ooh, good question!</p>
<h3>Should We (the Analysts) Do Blogs, and Can We Charge For Them?</h3>
<p>Yes (lots of decent bloggers out there already in analyst-land), and I
don’t know.</p> 
<h2 id='p-7'>The Analysts’ Future</h2>
<p>Obviously, this whole blogging thang has to be changing the playing field
these guys are on.
Which way?
I have no idea, although I think we’ll still need a community of interpreters.
But if there’s still an analysts’ summit in five years, I
bet it’s going to be a different kind of thing.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Arts/Photos</cat>
<title>A Chair</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Hey, this is my space, if I want to run a picture of a chair I can.
And it’s a <em>nice</em> chair.</p>
<img src="IMG_3248.jpg" alt="A chair, with shadow" />
<p>This is somewhere on the Sun Menlo Park campus.</p>
</body>
</letter>
<letter>
<head>
<cat>Arts/Photos/Scanned</cat>
<cat>Arts/Books</cat>
<cat>The World/Places/Wales</cat>
<title>FSS: Aberystwyth At Dusk</title>
</head>
<body>
<p>Friday Slide Scan #3 is from 1988: a dark waterfront in Wales, and a
side-trip into the Black Book of Carmarthen.</p>
<img src="1110.jpg" alt="Aberystwyth by night" />
<p>There’s a story that goes with this one.
At this point I was working on the Oxford English Dictionary project and,
since I was traveling to Britain often, combined one trip with a driving
vacation around the South and West.
I had been in contact with the
<a href="http://www.aber.ac.uk/~gpcwww/index.html">Geiriadur Prifysgol
Cymru</a> or Dictionary of the Welsh Language, who had been looking at some
of the same problems faced by the OED.
Since we were planning to drive through Wales, I offered to drop by.
We had a nice afternoon talking about computational lexicography.</p>
<p>The dictionary was at that time in the National Library, which also houses
some famous books including the
<a href="http://www.llgc.org.uk/drych/drych_s005.htm">Black Book of
Carmarthen</a>. 
So when we were finished, I asked the guys if the Black Book were on display,
because I’d like to go see it.
They said “It’s not on display, but that’s OK” and we wandered through the
basement hallways to the vault, went in, and they took it off the shelves and
put it in my hands!
It’s astounding; the 750-year-old illuminations looked like they’d been done
yesterday, colour and lustre leaping off the page.
No, I didn’t take a picture.</p>
<p>Images in the Friday Slide Scans are from 35mm slides taken between 1955
and 2003 by (in rough chronological order)
<a href="http://www.textuality.com/BillBray/">Bill Bray</a>, Tim Bray, Cath
Bray, and
<a href="http://www.laurenwood.org/anyway/">Lauren Wood</a>; when I know
exactly who took one, I’ll say.
Most but not all of the slides were on Kodachrome; they were digitized using
a Nikon CoolScan 4000 ED scanner and cleaned up by a combination of the Nikon
scanning software and PhotoShop Elements.</p>
</body>
</letter>
</ong>
